Guide to the Mabou Mines Archive, 1966-2000 (bulk 1970-1995) MSS.133
Fales Library and Special Collections
Mabou Mines Archive
1966-2000
1970-1995
Fales Library and Special Collections
Mabou Mines (Theater group)
MSS.133
161 Linear Feet in 158 boxes, 4 folders in shared housing, and 3 flat file folders
Beginning in 1970 Mabou Mines helped revolutionize experimental theatre in the United States and contributed to an international movement in avant-garde, postmodern theatre. The Mabou Mines create multi-media performances utilizing both existing texts and building performances utilizing a pastiche style that draws on a variety of sources. The materials in the collection document this creative process and the administrative functions necessary to maintain and promote the company.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Fales Library purchased the Mabou Mines Archive from the Mabou Mines Development Foundation in 2003. In 2019 a trunk of posters was located in the repository, accessioned separately, and integrated into the collection as Series XV.
Historical Note
Mabou Mines is a collaborative, avant-garde theater company based in New York City. Founded in 1970, the company took its name from an old mining town in northern Nova Scotia, near where founding members JoAnne Akalaitis, Lee Breuer, Philip Glass, Ruth Maleczech, and David Warrilow, developed The Red Horse Animation, the group's first original performance piece. Since then Mabou Mines has produced scores of plays, collaborated with well-known writers, musicians, visual artists, and filmmakers, garnered heaps of critical praise and awards, and performed around the globe, cementing its reputation as an innovative force in the theater world. The company's official website is maboumines.org.
Lee Breuer and Ruth Maleczech met studying theater at UCLA in the late 1950s. Around 1960, the couple hitchhiked to San Francisco to participate in the city's active theater scene. Working at the San Francisco Actor's Workshop and the San Francisco Mime Troupe they met Bill Raymond, and at the San Francisco Tape Music Center they met JoAnne Akalaitis. In 1964 Akalaitis moved to New York City but left for Paris soon after with composer (and future husband) Philip Glass. The following year Breuer and Maleczech left San Francisco for Europe. The two couples met up while traveling in Greece, went back to Paris, and with actor David Warrilow, began to work on staging Samuel Beckett's Play. It premiered at the American Cultural Center in 1967. It was also in Paris that the group first met actor Frederick Neumann. In 1969, back in New York with Glass, Akalaitis wrote the others in Paris suggesting they form a theater group in New York.
"Mabou Mines came together as a group to create formal works that would explore language and acting. They had a strong desire to collectively exercise complete artistic control over the work."1 Influenced especially by Jerzy Grotowski's teaching and Beckett's work, Mabou Mines went on to produce experimental theater pieces like Breuer's Red Horse Animation pieces that resulted from intense collaboration and improvisation, and incorporated elements of visual art, dance, mime, puppetry, and music. Arc Welding Piece (1972), for example, featured an artist using an arc welder to make cuts in a large piece of metal, while actors expressed various states of emotion, their faces enlarged by magnifying lenses. In 1974, Fred Neumann joined the group to work on Breuer's second "Animation," The B. Beaver Animation. Bill Raymond joined shortly thereafter.
In its early years, Mabou Mines moved easily between the art world and the theater, often performing in galleries as well as stages. But its work with Beckett's writing firmly situated the group within a theatrical context. "Mabou Mines has produced eight pieces by Samuel Beckett [ Cascando, Come and Go, Company, Imagination Dead Imagine, The Lost Ones, Mercier and Camier, Play, Worstward Ho], six of which have been world premieres of texts not originally written for the theatre. These productions have led to Mabou Mines being considered one of the foremost interpreters of Beckett's work."2 After an early residency at La Mama Experimental Theatre Club in New York, the company began performing at Joseph Papp's New York Shakespeare Festival Public Theater, and other venues in New York and elsewhere.
From the beginning, creative roles were fluid and collaboration was key, but Lee Breuer served as the company's primary director. In 1975 however, Akalaitis directed Cascando and opened the door for other members to take on new roles, for the company to expand, and for multiple projects to come together simultaneously. Akalaitis went on to direct Dressed Like an Egg (1977) and Southern Exposure (1979), and wrote and directed Dead End Kids (1980); Neumann directed Mercier and Camier (1979); Maleczech directed Vanishing Pictures (1980). Other performers worked with Mabou Mines, including L.B. Dallas, Linda Hartinian, Ellen McElduff, Greg Mehrten, Terry O'Reilly, and B-St. John Schofield.
The company steadily expanded its repertoire and continued its tradition of collaboration, working with talented performers and artists, including composers Bob Telson, John Zorn, Pauline Oliveros, and David Byrne. Mabou Mines has adapted works by Shakespeare ( Lear, 1990), Franz Xaver Kroetz ( Through the Leaves, 1984; Help Wanted, 1986), Philip K. Dick ( Flow My Tears, The Policeman Said, 1985), and Bertolt Brecht ( In the Jungle of Cities, 1991). The company has toured extensively in the United States and abroad.
Mabou Mines has remained committed to its ideal of complete artistic control. "All decisions, artistic and administrative, large and small, are made by the company members, and each member functions variously as producer, designer, actor, writer, or director for the other. Additionally all participate as members of the Board of Directors."3
As the company stated in a 1990 press kit, "The artistic purpose of Mabou Mines has been and remains the creation of new theatre pieces from original texts and the theatrical use of existing texts staged from a specific point of view. Each member is encouraged to pursue his or her artistic vision by initiating and collaborating on a wide range of projects of varying styles, developing them from initial concept to final performance. This process is intense and often lengthy. While the director of a Mabou Mines work is responsible for its concept and its basic structure, the ultimate production reflects the concerns and the artistic input of all its collaborators."4
References:
1. Unknown author, unpublished manuscript. A history of Mabou Mines through 1989.
2. Mabou Mines, company history included in press kit, 1990.
3. Mabou Mines website, maboumines.org.
4. Mabou Mines, company history included in press kit, 1990.
Chronology of Productions:
1970 The Red Horse Animation
1971 Come and Go
Play
1972 Arc Welding
Music for Voices
1973 Send/Receive/Send
1974 Mabou Mines Performs Samuel Beckett
1975 Cascando
The B. Beaver Animation
1976 The Saint and the Football Player
1977 Dressed Like An Egg
1978 Shaggy Dog Animation
1979 Mercier and Camier
Southern Exposure
1980 A Prelude to a Death in Venice
Dead End Kids
Easy Daisy (for radio)
Sister Suzie Cinema
Vanishing Pictures
1981 Wrong Guys
1982 The Keeper Radio Series
1983 Cold Harbor
Company
Hajj
The Joey Schmerda Story (for radio)
The Josy Schmerda
1984 Imagination Dead Imagine
Pretty Boy
Through the Leaves
1985 Flow My Tears the Policeman Said
It's A Man's World
Starcock
The Interview Series (for radio)
1986 CEO
Dead End Kids (Film Version)
Help Wanted
The Kafka Parables (for radio)
Worstward Ho
1987 Sueños
1988 The Gospel at Colonus
1990 B. Beaver Animation (reconstruction)
Mabou Mines Lear
The Miller Series (for radio)
1991 In the Jungle of Cities
The Quantum
1992 The MahabharANTa, and Selected Stories from the Insectiad
1993 The Bribe
1994 Mother
Reel To Real
1995 An Epidog
1996 Peter and Wendy
Pootanah Moksha
Red Horse Animation (reconstruction)
1997 Happy Days
1999 Belén-A Book of Hours
2000 Animal Magnetism
2001 Ecco Porco
2003 Cara Lucia
Mabou Mines DollHouse
2005 Red Beads
Summa Dramatica
2007 Song For New York: What Women Do While Men Sit Knitting
Scope and Contents
The Mabou Mines Archive contains an extremely diverse array of materials that comprehensively document the first 25 years of Mabou Mines, the New York City-based avant-garde theater company. The collection includes materials that document the innovative methods used by Mabou Mines to create unique theatrical adaptations from existing, often classical texts. Collaboration is a key element of Mabou Mines's artistic vision. All decisions, artistic and administrative, large and small, are made by the company members, and each member functions variously as producer, designer, actor, writer, or director. Additionally, all participate as members of the Board of Directors. Materials in the archive reflect this intensely collaborative environment.
The collection contains a wealth of production materials that document all aspects of theatrical production. It includes invaluable administrative records that reflect how the organization sustained, promoted, and financially supported its mission. Also included are scripts, programs, photographic documentation, production books and touring files, and extensive video documentation of most productions. As one of the leading interpreters of the literary works of Samuel Beckett, the collection contains correspondence between Beckett and Ruth Maleczech and Lee Breuer.
Known for their innovative incorporation of technology in theatrical productions, the Mabou Mines Archive contains extensive film, video, and audio production elements and supporting documentation.
The collection will be of interest to researchers working in the areas of avant-garde performance, performance art, experimental theatre, New York theater history and artistic collaborations, as well as to researchers examining the contemporary intersection between experimental theater, mime, music, poetry and the visual arts.
Numerous oversize items found at the end of each of the series include design plots, posters, oversize printed matter and other promotional materials housed in boxes and map cases.
Arrangement
For the most part, materials are arranged alphabetically. Production related materials are arranged alphabetically by production title with subseries for materials documenting different performance venues arranged chronogically. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Photographs and slides are arranged alphabetically by the name of the subject or production title that the materials document. Scripts and production books are arranged alphabetically by production title. Videorecordings are also arranged alphabetically by production title.
Series XII: Financial Files, Grants and Development and Series XIII: Administrative Files were processed at the box level.
All efforts were made to preserve the original arrangement of the collection.
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Programs
Series III: Production Files
Series IV: Photographs
Series V: Slides
Series VI: Scripts
Series VII: Production Books
Series VIII: Touring Files
Series IX: Video Recordings
Series X: Press
Series XI: Objects
Series XII Financial Files, Grants and Development
Series XIII: Administrative Files
Series XIV: Audio
Series XVI. Posters
Oversize - Series III: Production Files
Oversize - Series IV: Photographs
Oversize Series VIII: Touring Files
Oversize - Series X: Press
Oversize - Series XII: Financial Files, Grants and Development
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Separated Material
One copy of the comic book adaptation of Red Horse Animation was removed and catalogued individually in the Fales Library's Downtown Print and Periodicals Collection. This item has been cataloged in Bobcat, NYU's online catalog.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Advertisements.; Minutes (administrative records); Black-and-white photographs.; Drama.; Theater |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |v Sources.; Off Off-Broadway theater.; Calendars.; Ground plans.; Schematic drawings.; Motion pictures |z United States.; Negatives (photographic); Puppet theater.; Color slides.; Design drawings.; Videocassettes.; Grant proposals.; Art, Modern |z United States |y 20th century |v Exhibitions.; Experimental theater -- New York (State) -- New York.; Posters.; Color photographs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Audiotapes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Scores.; Scripts (documents); Poetry.; Financial records; Playbills.; New York (N.Y.); Theater -- New York (State) -- New York -- Reviews; Contact sheets.; 16mm; Puppet theater |z Bali Island (Indonesia); Nuclear energy |x History |v Drama.; Reviews (document genre); Press releases.; Membership lists.; Announcements.; Correspondence.; Brooklyn Academy of Music; Breuer, Lute (Ramblin'); Colette, 1873-1954; Byrne, David, 1952-; Boston Musica Viva; Blackwell, Byeager; Breuer, Lee; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-1956; Akalaitis, JoAnne; Bedrosian, Georgina; Beckett, Samuel, 1906-1989; Fergusson, Honora; Ellen Jacobs & Co; Eakland, Ann; Dick, Philip K.; Godfrey, Marion; Glass, Philip; Garfein, Herschel; Galilee, Clove; La Mama Experimental Theatre Club; Kroetz, Franz Xaver, 1946-; Hedstrom, Cynthia; Hartinian, Linda; Mabou Mines (Theater group); Mangolte, Babette; Whitney Museum of American Art; Maleczech, Ruth; Mabou Mines Development Foundation, Inc; New York State Council on the Arts; Landry, Richard; National Endowment for the Arts; Neumann, Frederick; McElduff, Ellen; Mehrten, Greg; O'Reilly, Terry; Oliveros, Pauline, 1932-; New York Shakespeare Festival Public Theater; Performing Artservices, Inc; Raymond, William; Ontological-Hysteric Theatre; Papp, Joseph; Strahs, James; Telson, Bob; Rosegg, Carol; Stewart, Ellen, 1920?-; Vawter, Ron; Vasconcellos, Anthony; Warrilow, David; Walker Art Center; Wexner Center for the Arts; Westbeth Theatre Center (New York, N.Y.); Wija, I Wayan; Yerxa, Alison; Worsley, Dale, 1948-; Zorn, John, 1953-
- Series I: Correspondence, 147445
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains documentation of the formation of the company and its early history, fan mail and other matters. Of particular interest are letters between the playwright Samuel Beckett and company members. The series also includes correspondence with Ellen Stewart, artistic director of LaMaMa E.T.C.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence with individuals, 147470
    Most of the contents were originally contained in a brown accordion file folder with alphabetical tabs.
    - Adler, Sebastian; Houston Institute of Contemporary Art; August 2, 1972, 147553 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Theatre Wing; November 4, 1983, 147552 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Arthurs, Alberta; Rockefeller Foundation; July 7, 1989, 147551 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Beckett, Samuel writing to Lee Breuer; March 8, 1976, 147550 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Beckett, Samuel writing to David Warrilow; April 30, 1978; photocopies, 147549 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Beckett, Samuel writing to Lee Breuer; October 26, 1981, 147548 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Maleczech, Ruth writing to Samuel Beckett; December 16, 1981; photocopies, 147547 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Beckett, Samuel writing to Ruth Maleczech; December 24, 1981, 147546 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Maleczech, Ruth writing to Samuel Beckett; March 12, 1984; photocopy, 147545 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Beckett, Samuel writing to Ruth Maleczech; March 23, 1984, 147544 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Maleczech, Ruth writing to Samuel Beckett; February 21, 1986; letter subsequently annotated by Beckett and returned to Ruth Maleczech, dated February 27, 1986, 147543 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Booth Trucking Service, undated; 147542 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bussard, Ellen; August 6, 1981, 147541 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Byers, Constance; March 30, 1971, 147540 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chase, Doris, undated; 147539 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Committee for National Theatre Week; April 26, 1982, 147538 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Council of Internation Exchange of Scholars; January 28, 1991, 147537 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Cowen, Allison; Dilemma; Southwestern at Memphis; March 1, 1972, 147536 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cultural Council Foundation, 1970-1971; 147535 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Daniels, Barry; Kent State University; August 10, 1985, 147534 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Danz, Caryn; New York Reception Center, United States Information Agency; re: Liliana Iorgulascu; September 3, 1993, 147533 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Downey, Roger; re: Uber die Dorfer, 1985; 147532 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Dramatists' Guild Fund; October 23, 1981, 147531 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Festivals Unlimited, undated; 147530 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Fish, Hamilton; The Nation; November 9, 1981, 147529 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Forsling, Stephen; June 20, 1990; plus undated FedEx slip, 147528 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Fuller, Mrs. Andrew P.; draft, undated; 147527 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Gerber, Tony; to Fred Neumann re: Reel to Real; August 23, 1993, 147526 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Gildzen, Alex; Kent State University Special Collections; August 27, 1985, 147525 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Green, Bill; Member of Congress; re: NEA grant; May 9, 1990, 147524 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Haddock, Angela M.; March 1, 1989, 147523 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Harrington, Jan R.; May 18, 1981, 147522 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Hayes, Patrick; JFK Center for Performing Arts, 1971; 147521 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Herman, Marie Louise; Winter Theatre, 1982; 147520 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Hill, Ray, undated; 147519 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Irving, Jules; Lincoln Center Repertory Company; August 2, 1972, 147518 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Ishiko, Eiko; November 10, undated; 147517 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Jakobson, Barbara; The Jakobson Foundation; February 14, 1973; May 14, 1973, 147516 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Japan-United States Friendship Commission, etc.; re: Creative Artist Fellowship for Japan, 1983-1988; 147515 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Katz, Mel; Portland State University; August 17, 1971, 147514 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Killoch, John; Walker Art Center; re: "The Mormon Project"; January 7, 1989, 147513 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Knaub, Richard K.; Univeristy of Colorado; May 1971, 147512 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Kryszak, Al; re: Mabou Mines Archive, undated; 147511 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Kuku Ryku Theatre Laboratory; August 17, 1979, 147510 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Lindsley, Carol; The Gallery Reese Palley; August 3, 1971, 147509 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Lovelace, Carey; re: Dead End Kids article; April 7, 1983, 147508 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - MacIntyre, Tom; December 17, 1986, 147507 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - McIlwain, Traci; December 14, 1993, 147506 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Marsee, Judy; Reed College Dance Department; January 21, 1972, 147505 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Mehta, Xerxes; University of Maryland; September 4, 1984, 147504 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Monsod, Trinket; The House Foundation; September 20, 1982, 147503 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - National Endowment for the Arts; April 12, 1976, 147502 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - National Endowment for the Arts; August 8, 1976, 147501 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - National Endowment for the Arts; October 1, 1987, 147500 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - National Endowment for the Arts; International Program; FONCA; November-December, 1994, 147499 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - New York Foundation for the Arts, Inc.; April 1972, 147498 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - New York Supreme Court; re: jury duty; May/July 1982, 147497 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Orchand, Robert J.; American Repertory Theatre Company; May 10, 1981, 147496 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Oyston, Peter; Victorian College of Art; July 15, 1981, 147495 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Papp, Joseph; New York Shakespeare Festival; October 19, 1979, 147494 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Papp, Joseph; October 6, 1981, 147493 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Pinney, Marguerite; Vancouver Art Gallery; October 1971, 147492 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Poole, Kathy; February-March, 1984, 147491 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Prefer, Morty; Royal Offset; March 1983, 147490 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Rent-A-Artist; July 25, 1971, 147489 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Reynolds, Edgar; University of California, Berkeley; March 1971, 147488 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Rich, Frank; re: Prelude to a Death in Venice; May 30, 1980, 147487 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Schaefer, Carla T.; New York State Council on the Arts; June 14, 1971, 147486 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Selz, Peter; University of California Art Museum; May 22, 1971, 147485 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Shank, Ted; August 2, 1972, 147484 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Stewar1, Ellen; LaMaMa, E.T.C.; August 4, 1972, 147483 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Sussman, Sally; November 3, 1993, 147482 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Swerdlove, Dorothy L.; New York Public Library; March 2, 1989, 147481 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Takahashi, M.; January-February, 1982, 147480 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Theaterschool, Amsterdam; re: Internships at Mabou Mines; January 26, 1983, 147479 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - United States Government Printing Office; October 14, 1982, 147478 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Vinton, James; St. James Editorial Ltd.; re: Contemporary Dramatists entry; September-October, 1981, 147477 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Wurlitzer, Rudolph; July 8, 1971, 147476 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Mabou Mines intra-company correspondence; David to Jane, from Delaware, Ohio, 1975; 147475 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Miscellaneous Mabou Mines intra-company correspondence, 1989; undated; 147474 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Letters accompanying scripts, 1980-1987; 147473 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Letters to photographers, photo shops, 1976-1994; 147472 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 147471 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence about productions, 147446
    - Cold Harbor; fan mail; November 9, 1985, 147469 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Company; January 11, 1983, 147468 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Dead End Kids; January-February, 1983, 147467 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Epidog; January 11, 1996, 147466 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Gospel at Colonus, 1990; 147465 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Hajj, 1983; 147464 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Hajj; Prelude to a Death in Venice; December 27, 1984, 147463 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Lear, 1988, 1990; 147462 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Lear, undated; 147461 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Lost Ones; re: rights, etc., 1975-1978; 147460 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Mercier and Camier Grove Press, 1977-1979; 147459 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Play; permissions, 1972; 147458 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Play; Come and Go Grove Press; April-July, 1971, 147457 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Prelude to a Death in Venice, 1980, 1981; 147456 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Pretty Boy; September 21, 1984, 147455 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Red Horse Animation, 1970; 147454 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Reel to Real; David Latham; April 11, 1994, 147453 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Reel to Real; October 10, 1994, 147452 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - The Saint and the Football Player; August 26, 1976, 147451 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Shaggy Dog Animation; October 18, 1977, 147450 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Sueños; fan mail; February-March, 1989, 147449 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - The Tempest; August 5, 1981, 147448 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Through the Leaves; October-November, 1984, 147447 (Box 2, Folder 106)
- Series II: Programs, 147301